Now that we have images in the computer represent us, we learn in the previous
利用上一个视频讲到的离散二维数组
video discrete 2-dimensional arrays. Basically, we started from a continuous
计算机可以这样描绘出图像
picture and we finish with the 2-dimension discrete array.
也就是我们从这张连续的图片 得到了这个二维离散数组
Now, we can start doing operations on these images.
现在我们就可以对这些图片进行处理了
There are network computer, there are just 2-dimensional arrays of pixels we
现在图像在我们的电脑中 它们可被看成像素的二维数组
can do very different types of operations to do the kind of things that we saw in
我们就能够基于此进行各种各样的处理
the first couple of videos in this class. During the next few weeks, we're going to
就如我们前几节课视频看到的那样 在接下来几周里
learn very sophisticated operations. But let's start with just a few very
我们将会学到一些非常复杂的操作 我们先从一些简单的例子开始
simple ones that, they are very simple but they are extremely useful and will
它们虽然简单但却非常有用
tell us how we actually can manipulate images.
能够让我们知道如何真正地处理这些图片
And you can go into your computer and do any of the examples that I'm going to
你也可以用自己的电脑 来实践我一会给大家演示的例子
show in the next few slides in just a few minutes or, or even less if you have a, a
如果你有MATLAB这样的软件 这只需要几分钟时间或者更短
program like Mathlab that are natural to work with 2-dimensional arrays.
MATLAB 是一种常被用来处理二维数组的软件
Once we have a 2-dimensional array, one of the things that we can start talking
当有了一个二维矩阵 我们可以就开始
is about neighborhoods. So remember, we have a 2-dimensional
探讨邻域处理 要记住 我们有一个二维数组
array, and we're talking about pixels. So, this
现在我们要在像素层面探讨 在这里我画了一个像素点
is a pixel, and I can ask where are the neighbors of this pixel.
我要问哪些像素和这个像素相邻
And there are two types of standard neighborhoods that are taken in image
这里介绍图像处理中的两种邻域
processing. One is called a four neighborhood, and
一种称之为 “4邻域”
only these four are considered. And that's basically, you can only go
只包含画出的这四个点 也就是说你只能
North, South, East, or West, so it's just a four neighborhood.
去找上下左右的四个像素 所以这就是 4领域
There is another very popular that is an eight neighborhood,
另一种常见的类型就是 “8邻域”
and you probably already guessed how it works.
你或许已经猜出来是怎么回事了
So, if I'm here, the neighbors, the A neighbors of this
如果是这个像素点 就要取环绕着它的所有相邻像素
pixel are all the pixels around it. So, you can go north and south, east and
你可以和刚才一样 看到上下左右的点
west, as before. But you can also go like northeast and
你也可以看到像左上角 这样的对角邻像素
start going diagonal. So, for example, if I look at this image
举个例子 看看这张图
here, this pixel, in a four neighborhood relationship is
这个像素的 4邻域像素中
not a neighbor of this one. So, these two 1s are not neighbors.
不包括这个点 因此 这两个 1 不相邻
Because I cannot go diagonal in a four neighborhood relationship.
这是因为4邻域关系 并不包括对角线位置的点
In an eight neighborhood relationship, there are neighbors.
而在8邻域像素关系中 它们就是相邻像素了
And that of course translates also to a group of pixels.
当然 这个概念也可以迁移用于像素组中
So, this group of pixels has an eight neighborhood relationship with this one.
上面这个像素组和下面的这个像素组存在8邻域的关系
Because there is a one here, and a one diagonal.
因为有一个 1 在这儿 而另一个 1 在它的对角线上
And I'm allowed to go diagonal, okay?
这时可以考虑对角线上的点
Now, if I were to talk about fourth neighborhood, I will say that this group
现在 如果我们考虑的是4邻域的话 我可以说
of ones is not neighbor of this group of ones.
上面这一组 1 与下面这一组 1 是不相邻的
Because from this one, I can only go south.
因为从这个 1 出发 我们只能向下找
I don't see anybody from this group, any ones.
在下面这个组中 我看不到和它相邻的“1”
I can go right, east, I don't see anybody.
在这个 1 的右边 也没有 1
So basically, depending on how we define neighborhood in this discrete space,
因此 我们能够进行什么样的操作取决于在这个离散空间中
what kind of operations we can do. And were going to see that's very important.
是如何定义邻域的 我们将会看到这很重要
This is the most common neighborhood today used in most modern image
这种邻域 在现代图像处理中最为常见
processing. But it's important to be aware of this
但是了解这种领域也很重要
type of neighborhood. Especially, when we're going to be doing
尤其是在我们进行图像分割或者类似的操作时
segmentation and things like that. We're also going to, later on when we
再比如说 我们今后会谈到
talk about the last week, we're going to talk about 3D images.
我们会讲解 三维图像
So, not images that have a great values on the plane,
不是那种平面上的有灰度值的图像
like here, where every pixel has a great value.
就像这样 每个像素都有一个灰度值的这个平面
But we're going to talk about volumetric images where every point in the volume,
但是我们将要说到的体积图像 位于其空间内的每个点
those are going to be called voxels have great values.
称之为 体素 (voxel) 都有灰度值
And the neighborhood relationships are very important there, for example, in
邻域关系对于这种图像而言非常重要
medical images, to decide that this organ is neighbor to
比如说 在医学图像中 判断这个器官和另一个器官是否相邻
this organ, we're going to have to define the neighborhood relationships.
我们就需要界定邻域关系
And the same when we're going to do segmentation.
在图像分割的时候 也是如此
So, neighborhoods are important. But now that we have 2-dimensional
邻域如此重要 但现在我们仅就二维数组中进行讨论
arrays, we can do simple operations between 2-dimensional arrays.
我们对在二维数组 进行一些简单的操作
For example, we can add them. Remember, every point, so if I look at
比如说我们可以叠加它们 记住 每一个点 例如这张图
this image, every point here has a value. So, I can take that image and add to a
每个点都有相应的值 因此 我可以把这张图像叠加到第二张上
second image. So I can take image one,
所以我可以把图像一
and add it to image two. That means that I take, and I'm drawing a
加到图像二上 这就意味着 我特意在这画一个小图像
small image in purpo, on purpose, this is a three by three image.
图像为三行三列
I'm going to take the value here and add it to the value here.
我取这个点的值与另外这个点的值相加
So if here it say seven and here it say ten I'm going to get a result which is
我假设这个值是7 另一个的值是10 那么结果就是17
seventeen. Then, I go to the next pixel and I do the
下一个像素我也这么处理
same. It's a simple addition of images.
这种图像相加很简单
That's an extremely important operation by itself,
是一种简单却又很重要的处理方法
very simple. So here, we see that operation.
我们看看这个操作
We basically have NASA took images, multiple images, of the same galaxy.
这里有好几张NASA拍摄的同一个星系的图像
Multiple times, they go once, and again, and take more and more and more images.
他们拍摄 再拍摄  重复多次 得到越来越多的图像
The images are very noisy, but all the images are aligned.
这张图像噪点很多 这些图像排列在一起
So they don't move the camera and nothing is moving.
他们不移动相机 什么都不变
They take one after the other, and then they start adding them.
然后一张接一张拍摄 再叠加起来
And, when they add the image, when they add the images, they start getting
随着他们对图像的叠加 图像开始变得越来越清晰
clearer and clearer. So here, they basically added five,
因此这里 他们叠加了五张
then they added ten, so on until they got a hundred images.
然后又叠加十张 直到叠加了100张
So, they did I1 + I2 a hundred times. So, they have a hundred images of this galaxy
也就是他们把 I1+I2 的操作进行了100次
and they added them together. And what happens is the image starts
就是把一百张的星系图片 叠加到一起
becoming clearer and clearer because the image has noise.
使得得到的图像开始变得越来越清晰 这是因为图像有噪声
The image is always, the actual scene is always the same scene.
这些图像中的场景固定不变
The noise is the one that changes, that changes, and when you add all those
这些噪声却不断变化 当你把图片都叠加起来
images, you're adding the same number, plus the noise that is random, and then
相当于叠加了图片中拍摄对象的像素值 而噪声又是随机的
the noise gets reduced. And when we talk about spatial noisy, and
这样噪声就显得微不足道了 当我们讨论如何处理空间噪声
how to do image enhancing, we're going to discuss this very, very in detail.
以及讨论如何增强图像的时候 我们将非常详细地讨论这个话题
But the basic idea is that we can simply add this 2-dimensional race to do a
那么基本思路就是 我们可以简单地将一些二维数组相加
number of interesting operations. We can do other things.
从而完成一些有趣的处理 我们还可以做其他的事情
Basically, we can also mask them. We can subtract them.
我们还可以对图像进行掩模处理或者相减运算
So, we can have an image like this, and our image like this. Let's say, two
我们可以看到这幅图像 还有这幅图像
variations of the same scene, but taken under different conditions.
这是同一场景在不同情况下拍摄的两张图像
And then, we take the difference between them.
接下来 我们找出了它们之间的差别
And look, the difference shows something that might
你看 这个凸显出来的不同之处
be very, very important for the doctor. And this is just an enhance that we're
可能对于医生来讲非常非常重要 而这是增强以后的图像
going to talk about this, we enhance images for example by changing the grey
我们往后会讲到如何增强图像
value distributions to make them more clear.
例如 通过改变灰度值的分布使其更加清晰
So, in this case, we take, we took I1, I2, and we basically did I1 - I2.
那么这里 上面两幅图我们标记为 I1、I2 然后进行了 I1-I2
Sometimes, we take the absolute value if you don't, if we don't care about the
如果不关心正负的话 我们有时候也会取绝对值
sign. And sometimes, we just basically shift
有时 我们只是移走所有负数值的像素
all the pixels so the negative value become zero.
这样就把负值都变成了 0
once again, a very simple operation that can have tremendous value.
这再一次证明了这种简单的操作也具有重要意义
Some, we can also do logic operations in images.
有时 我们也可以对图像进行逻辑运算
So we can have basically, an image A and our image B, and do AUB.
我们可以对图像A和图像B 做A并B的运算
So basically, we, let's say that this is all 255, the rest
让我们假设这部分 (A部分) 的值都是255
is zero. B again, is all 255, so we get the union
其余部分都是0 B部分的值也全部是255
of them. We get the interception of the pixels
然后得到并集 这个图我们得到了交集
that both objects have 255 or Y values. So again, think about any type of
即 在A和B中 值为255或者白色值的所有像素
operations that you could do with 2-dimensional arrays in your computer.
同理 想一想用你的电脑你可以对二维数组进行哪些运算
You can start doing with images, now that we know that there are nothing else in
你也可以对图像进行相同操作 现在我们知道了
the computer than 2-dimensional arrays. We can also basically take the inverse of
用计算机操作二维数组是多么重要 我们还能对一幅图像进行反相
an image, and the basic idea is that this remember was zero, very black.
基本思想是 这部分特别黑的地方是0
The brightest point, 255.
最亮的这个点是255
And then, we can actually invert it. We can make the zero go to 255,
然后我们可以进行反相 将0变成255
and the 255 go to zero. It would be a map like this.
将255变成0 在坐标里表示就是这样
If this is the input and this is the output,
假设横轴是输入 纵轴是输出
it would be something like this. A zero goes to 255, 255 goes to zero.
画出来就是这样的 0对应成255 255对应成0
So we invert the image, and then we can, using that we can find some interesting
我们对图像反相操作 利用这个我们可以发现一些有趣的事情
things and that might be easier to observe certain objects in the image in
也许反相后的图像会比原来的图像
the inverted image than it was in the original image.
更容易从中观察到一些对象
Again, a simple operation with the arrays that we have representing our images in
总结一下 数组的这些简单操作可通过计算机运用于图像处理之中
the computer. We can also do different spatial.
我们也能做不同的空间操作
So, this was adding images. So I take an image,
比如图像叠加 我用一张图片
I take another image, I add it.
再拿另一张图片 然后相加
Or, I invert an image. But, we can do more sophisticated things.
或是图像反相之类 但是我们还能做一些更复杂的事情
We can actually take a pixel in the image, and replace it by the average of
事实上我们还可以把图像中一个像素替换为的与之相邻像素的平均值
its neighbors. Now remember, I have to define what our
注意 需要先定义相邻像素的类型
neighbors, okay?
好的？
So, let's consider an eight neighborhood, as we talk before.
因此 我们可以设为 8邻域 我们之前讲到过这个
So I can take this pixel and replace it by the average of everybody, including
我可以把这个像素替换为所有像素的平均值 也包括它自己
itself. So, we just sum all the pixel values.
因而我们只要把所有像素的值相加
We divide by nine and we replace that pixel by that result,
然后再除以9 把得到的数值赋给这个像素
okay? And this is the original image.
这个是原图
We do that for every single one of the pixels.
我们把每一个像素点都做了这样的处理然后是这样
So, we go to this pixel. I'm going to mark it here.
所以对于这个像素 我把它标记在这里
We go to it's eight neighborhood, and we replace the value of the pixel by the
我们找到了它的 8邻域 然后把这个像素替换为
pixels by the average of the pixels around it.
周围所有像素的平均值
Then, we go to the next pixel, and we do the same.
然后对于下一个像素 我们也这样做
Then, we do the overlapping. I'm going to just use a different color
这里发生了交叠 我用另外一个颜色标出来
here. So, this one will use this, this, this,
因此 这个像素会用到这个 这个 这个
this, this, this, this, and this. While the blue one has used this one,
这个 这个 这个 这个 还有这个 蓝色的点则用到了这个
this one, this one. So it's owned eight neighborhood,
这个和这个 这是它自己的 8邻域
okay? So, there is overlapping because we are shifting one pixel at a time.
之所以会交叠 是因为我们一次变换一个像素
And then, we do that for every single pixel in the image.
然后我们对图像中每个像素都是这样一个一个处理
You are very welcome to try this exercise.
极力推荐你做一下这个小练习
And this is what we get. We removed the noise but we also get a
这就是我们得到的结果 我们移除了噪点
very blurry image. And we are going to see why that happens.
但却得到一张很模糊的图像 我将会说明为什么会这样
This is a very useful image processing application in some cases.
在一些情况下 这是一种的很有用的图像处理应用
We're are actually going to learn how to do this.
我们将会了解这是怎么实现的
So, we actually take neighbhor hoods, but they're sophisticated neighborhoods in
我们所选取的相邻像素 事实上并非那么简单
the sense that they understand when there is a big change and they don't go to the
当像素间变化比较大时 我们不会用到另一边的像素
other side. So we're going to basically, may be end
因此 最终可能只用了 6个像素进行平均
up averaging only these six, instead of always averaging nine values.
而不是通常 9个像素的平均
But this is a very simple operation. Every pixel replace it by a linear
这是一种非常简单的操作 每个像素被替换为一种线性组合
combination, in this case an average of the pixels around it.
在这里 就是指替换为周围像素的平均值
The other thing that can happen to images, is they can be transformed.
另一种图像处理方式是图像变换
And we can do very different type of transformations.
我们可以做各种不同的图像变换
We can, so, if this is my image, we can do nothing to it.
这个是我们没有变化的原始图像
We can actually scale it just make it larger.
我们可以对它进行缩放 比如使其变大
We can rotate, we can shift it or translate many, many
我们也可以让图像旋转、移动、平移等等
operations so we can take that array and move it.
我们可以用数组进行平移变换
We can take that array and rotate it. We can take that array and scale it.
我们还可以用数组进行旋转变换和缩放变换
Again, these are all 2-dimensional arrays in the computer so we can do any of these
它们都是计算机中的二维数组 因此我们可以进行任意的这些操作
operations. And here's what will happen, so we are
这就是操作的效果 如果我们要旋转图像
going to rotate the image. So, we take this T, we rotate the whole
我们要进行旋转变换 我们把 T 所在的图像整个旋转
image, but like we see some rotation of the T.
从而看上去这个 T 被旋转了一些角度
And here it says zoom in on the edge. And this illustrates again the issues
放大边缘看一下 这再一次说明了离散化的问题
with discretization. So, when I have a straight line in a
当我画一条直线的时候
discrete image, and this straight line goes here, it
放在这个离散化的图像中 如果是这么竖直画的话
looks very nice. But when the straight line, as it happens
就不会有问题 但是 当一条直线这样画
here, goes around. Goes diagonal.
不位于中间 而是穿过对角线方向
It gets kind of truncated like we see it here,
就会产生像我们在这看到的这种不完整的效果
okay? And the more pixels we have, the less
像素点越多的话
we're going to notice this. But, now we're discussing just the
我们就越难察觉这种问题 这里我们只讨论旋转的可能后果
possibility of rotation, the possibility of different operations on images.
对图像进行不同操作的可能后果
And here is the full example and I want you to basically look at, at this.
这是一个完整的例子 我希望你能看看它
So this is my original image, we rotate it.
这是我的原始图像 这是旋转后的图像
We can rotate it back. It looks perfect to us, although it has
我们也可以把它转回来 看上去还算不错
some differences. This is the difference between these two
但还是有些不同 这是两幅图像的不同之处
images, okay? So, if I were to write down what happened
如果要写出来这个过程
here, I had an image. I rotated it.
我有一张图 I 然后我旋转它 R(I)
I basically took this result, which is this.
这个的结果 就得到了这个图
And rotated it, in the opposite direction and obtained this, and then I subtracted
再朝相反方向旋转它 就能得到这幅图
these two. Basically, I subtracted I from this one.
然后两张图相减 也就是这个部分减去 I
So this is I, this is the rotation, this is the ris, the inverse rotation to the
这是 I  这是旋转后的图像 这是逆旋转的图像
result and this is the subtraction. And the reason we have difference is
这个是相减后的图像 两者不同的原因就是
because of this sampling, discretization of this phase that we discuss in the
因为采样和离散化 我们在之前的视频中讨论过
previous video. There's one more thing that we can do on
还有一点 我们可以实现的
images and we're going to basically discuss this next week when we talk about
将在下一周讲述关于图像压缩的话题时讨论
compression. We can actually do transforms to images.
我们可以对图像进行变换
And, those of you that already took the SP classes know that one of the transform
你们在数字信号处理的课程中已经知道了 有一种变换是
that we can do is a Fourier transform. So we have an image, we do a Fourier
傅里叶变换 (Fourier transform) 我们可以对一幅图像进行傅里叶变换
transform of it. And that's going to be very important in
而在图像压缩中非常重要的一点是
compression. We're not going to do Fourier, we're
我们不做傅里叶变换 我们要进行一种
going to do what's called the great cosine transform.
叫做离散余弦变换 (Discrete Cosine Transform) 的变换
So, this is an image. And, we are doing a Fourier transform of
这是一幅图像 我们对它进行傅里叶变换
it. This is the Fourier transform.
这是傅里叶变换后的图像
And now you see noise so where it can filter in the Fourier domain.
你现在所看到的是噪声能够在傅里叶域中滤除掉
And I haven't discussed any background in singular processing as Fourier.
我不在这讨论关于傅里叶的信号处理 (signal processing) 的背景知识
We are not going to need a lot of it. I'm going to discuss at every week the
而且我们也不需要了解很多 我将会在今后每周
background that we need for that week, and we are not going to do a lot of
的课程中讲到那周需要的背景知识 实际上我们也不会用到太多的傅里叶
fourier. So if you haven't, I mean we can do a lot
如果你不具备这些知识 那么不用傅里叶变换
of image processing without knowing Fourier transform.
我们也可以完成许多的图像处理
So, if you haven't taken any of the SP class, don't worry. We're going to be
因此 你也不必去上数字信号处理的课程 别担心
able to do everything but this slide without knowing fourier.
除了这一页幻灯片 我们不用傅里叶就可以完成所有事情
So, don't worry about that. But those of you that are familiar with
所以 不用担心 但如果你们熟悉傅里叶的话
Fourier, and you will see that I can filter these, for example this filter and
你就能看到滤波的效果 比如说 这个是滤波器
then return. So I do a transform,
这是处理后的结果 因此 我完成了变换
I filter and I come back and I get a very clean image.
经过滤波和逆变换 得到了一张非常清晰的图像
So, once again, those of you that are familiar with, with basic signal
再重复一遍 如果你们熟悉基本的关于傅里叶变换的信号处理知识
processing of Fourier transform, this is nothing else than a Fourier year filter.
这里也只会用到傅里叶滤波器
For those of you that are not familiar the thing that I took the image, I took
如果你们对此不太熟悉的话 你可以理解为我把这幅图像
that 2-dimensional array and I transform it into a different 2-dimensional array.
这个二维数组变换为另一个不同的二维数组
I did some manipulations there and I came back, and I got a very clean image back.
然后我进行了一些操作 然后又变换回来 我就得到了一张清晰的图像
And, once again, this is only to illustrate that what we are doing here is
再一次 这只是为了直观地展示我们所做的
operating with 2-dimensional arrays. Where at every point, we have a value
其实是对二维数组的运算 对于每个点 会有对应的值
that represents the brightness or the color in that particular location or in
这个值可以表示特定位置、像素的亮度或者颜色
that pixel. So, now we know we have images as
现在我们知道了图像
representing in the computer. Now,
在计算机中是如何表示的
we have seen already that the, that we want to have a lot of pixels, we want to
现在 我们发现如果我们想要很多像素
have a lot of grey values. And that's going to take a lot of space.
想有很多的灰度值 就需要占据很大的空间
And we're going to see in the next videos for the next week about compression,
因此 在下周的视频中 我们就来讨论压缩的问题
which is how do we deal with that large amount of data that we need to have very
怎样才能在保持图像质量的前提下处理大量的数据
good image quality. Thank you.
谢谢大家 //果壳教育无边界字幕组  showonder | 风过成伤 | 小白_远游